A Guide to the Walter E. Hoffman Papers, 1954-1992
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, Washington and Lee University
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, School of Law, Washington and Lee University
Walter E. Hoffman Papers 1954-1992
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, School of Law, Washington and Lee University
015
C. 100 cu. ft.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Walter E. Hoffman, May 16, 1995; received April 8, 2004.
Biographical/Historical Information
Walter Edward Hoffman was born in Jersey City, New Jersy and graduated in economics from the University of Pennsylvania in 1928. He received a law degree from Washington and Lee University in 1931 and went into private practice in Norfolk, Virgnia. He rose to leadership in the Virginia Republican Party and headed the state Republican convention in 1952. In 1954 President Dwight D. Eisenhower appointed him to the United States District Court for the Eastern District of irginia, sitting in Norfolk. Hightlights of Judge Hoffman's more than 40 years on the bench include the issuing of rulings to implement the Supreme Court mandate ending racial segregation; accepting Vice President Spiro T. Agnew's nolo contendere plea; and handling the corruption trial of District Court Judge Harry E. Claiborne. In recognition of his service, the Norfolk courthouse bears his name. Hoffman died on November 21, 1996.
Scope and Content
The Walter E. Hoffman papers suggest the breadth of his judicial service, with records from 8 U.S. Circuit courts and the U.S. Supreme Court in addition to those from the U.S. District Court, Eastern District of Virginia. His service in professional associations, most particularly the Judicial Conference of the United States is well documented. Unfortunately, there is a dirth of biographical information and many of his most memorable trials are not represented in the collection.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged by series with the professional association records and judicial case files making up almost 90% of the extent of the papers.
Contents List
- Biographical Materials, 1961-1997 (Carton 1)
- Correspondence, 1985-1990 (Carton 1)
- Subject Files, c.1980-1989 (Carton 1-3)
- Speeches, c. 1972-1985 (Carton 5-6)
- Law School Lectures (William & Mary), 1978 (Carton 7)
- Opinions 1954-1983 (Carton 8-12)
- Professional Associations 1960-1994
  - Judicial Conference of the United States
    - General, 1965-1994 (Carton 13-18)
    - Committees
      - Advisory Committee on Criminal Rules, 1961-1992 (Carton 19-27)
      - Cameras in the Courtroom, 1983-1984 (Carton 28-29)
      - Continuing Education, 1966 (Carton 30)
      - Jury System, 1960 (Carton 30)
      - Habeas Corpus, 1970-1977 (Carton 31-32)
      - Probation, 1963-1967 (Carton 33)
      - Rules of Practice and Procedure, 1970-1987 (Carton 34-36)
    - Seminar for New Judges, 1963 (Carton 37)
  - Federal Judicial Center, 1973-1984 (Carton 38-39)
  - Metropolitan Chief Judges, 1976-1983 (Carton 40-41)
- Jury Charges and Local Rules, 1979-1966 (Carton 42-44)
- Case Files, 1964-1993
  - U.S. District Courts
    - Eastern District of Virginia, 1964-1991
      - General, 1964-1990 (Carton 45-49)
      - U.S. v. Morgan Joe, 1991-1992 (Carton 50)
    - Western District of Virginia, 1986 (Carton 51)
    - Southern District of West Virginia (Arch Moore), c.1990 (Carton 52-53)
    - District of Massachusetts, 1974 (Carton 54)
    - District of South Carolina (U.S. v. Schaffer), 1981 (Carton 55)
    - Middle District of Florida (general), 1983-1989 (Carton 56-57; 61)
      - Mekdeci v. Merrill National Laboratories, 1981 (Carton 58)
      - Evans v. Orlando Central Park, 1985-1986 (Carton 59)
      - U.S. v. Murgo, 1983-1984 (Carton 60)
    - District of Utah, 1971-1973 (Carton 62)
  - U.S. Circuit Courts
    - 3rd Circuit, 1980-1984 (Carton 63-64)
    - 4th Circuit, 1983-1990 (Carton 65-70)
    - 7th Circuit, 1982 (Carton 71)
    - 9th Circuit, 1982-1983 (Carton 62-75)
    - 10th Circuit (Pacific Engineering v. Kerr-McGee), 1972-1973 (Carton 76-78)
    - 11th Circuit, 1982-1991 (Carton 79-94)
    - D.C. Circuit, 1978-1979 (Carton 95)
    - Temporary Emergency Court of Appeals, 1983-1993 (Carton 96-103)
  - U.S. Supreme Court
    - Georgia v. South Carolina, 1977-1988 (Carton 104-105)
    - U.S. v. Maine, 1977-1985 (Carton 106-107)